Guide to the John Nolen Jr. papers, 1906-2000 MS2193
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
John Nolen, Jr. papers
1906-2000
1935-1968
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Nolen, John
MS2193
20 Linear Feet
This collection contains materials related to the work of John Nolen as an urban planner in Washington D.C. The materials date from 1906-2000 with the bulk of the material falling between 1935 and 1968. The materials in this collection include official records from organizations such as the Committee of 100 on the Federal City and the National Capital Park and Planning Commission (now the National Planning Commission) for which John Nolen worked as well as material from organizations of which Nolen was a member such as the American Society of Civil Engineers and American Society of Landscape Architects. There are also records for various topics that Nolen dealt with during his career such as urban mass transit, housing (such as alley dwelling in Washington, D.C.) and highway transportation.
Oversize-folder UP1
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, publications, meeting minutes, reports, studies, and newsletters from the working life of urban planner John Nolen, Jr. The material dates from 1906 through 2000 with the bulk of the material falling between 1935 and 1968. The subjects in this collection include transportation including highways and subway systems, housing, and urban planning. Much of the material relates to the city of Washington with a subseries devoted to Nolen's work with the National Capital Park and Planning Commission, now known as the National Planning Commission.
Throughout his life, John Nolen Jr. was a member of many professional organizations such as the American Society of Civil Engineers, Washington Chapter of the American Institute of Planners, the American Planning and Civic Association, the Committee of 100 on the Federal City, and the Torch Club. Some of the records of his interaction with these organizations are part of this collection. Some of this material is from a professional relationship while others are personal.
Much of the material relates to the work life of John Nolen in his various capacities in the Federal Government and especially his time with the National Capital Park and Planning Commission. These records includes correspondence with government officials and speechs and articles written by Nolen for presentation at conferences.
Biographical / Historical
John Nolen Jr. (1898-1986) was the director of the National Capital Planning Commission from 1951-58. His work with the National Capital Planning Commission began in 1931 when the commission was called the National Park and Planning Commission. During his tenure, the Commission worked in the planning of parkways, highways, parks, playgrounds, and public buildings. He was supportive of the construction of the George Washington Parkway in both Virginia and Maryland, and supervised the preparations of early plans for what would become Metro.
Throughout his career, Nolen was a member of many professional societies including American Institute of Planners, American Society of Civil Engineers, American Society of Landscape Architects, American Society of Planning Officials, and International Fraternity of Lambda Alpha (Land economics). With the American Society of Civil Engineers, Nolen held various positions such as chairman of the City Planning Division, chairman of the Bicentennial Committee and chairman of the NCS City Planning and Urban Planning and Development Committees.
After leaving the National Planning Commission in 1958, Nolen became an independent planning consultant until he returned to government service in 1962 as Director of Transportation in what became the Department of Housing and Urban Development. He held this position for six years.
Much of his work was devoted to conservation of area water resources. He served on the Maryland State Water Quality Advisory Commission and was involved in the restoration efforts in Georgetown and other areas near the C&O Canal.
John Nolen Jr. was born in Ardmore, Pa., and earned a bachelor's degree in civil engineering from MIT. He died on June 20, 1986.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: Biography and correspondence, Planning organizations, Transportation, Housing and oversize maps and planning drawers.
Related Materials
John Nolen Jr.'s father, American Landscape Architect John Nolen, has his personal papers housed at Cornell University. http://rmc.library.cornell.edu/ead/htmldocs/RMM02903.html
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of John Nolen Jr., 1985.
City planning; City planning -- Washington (D.C.); Urban transportation; Transportation -- Washington Metropolitan Area; Urban renewal; Transportation; Housing; Urbanization; Nolen, John; United States. National Capital Park and Planning Commission; Alley Dwelling Authority (Washington, D.C.); Washington Housing Association; Committee of 100 on the Federal City (Washington, D.C.); National Research Council (U.S.). Highway Research Board; American Society of Civil Engineers; Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority; American Institute of Planners; American City Planning Institute; United States. National Capital Planning Commission; United States. National Capital Park Commission
- Biography and correspondence, 1921-1984; 1932-1961; Series 1; 2.5 Linear Feet
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence, newspaper clippings, articles, photographs, and brochures. The material in this series date from 1921-1984. The folders with correspondence contain letters and materials attached to the letters such as clippings, handwritten notes, and brochures. The folders with correspondence do at times have overlapping dates because the folders were most often maintained as received from the donor.
  - Civil service applications, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chronological file, 1962; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chronological file: Williamsburg, VA, 1966 March 2-4; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chronological file, 1963 December - 1965 January 12; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chronological file, 1965 January 12- 1965 April 14; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chronological file, 1965 April 15 - 1965 August 31; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chronological file, 1965 September 1 - 1965 December 30; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chronological file, 1966 January 1 - 1966 March 30; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chronological file, 1966 April 1 - 1966 July 20; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Columbia Historical Society [1/2], 1957-1975; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Columbia Historical Society [2/2], 1957-1975; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Comprehensive and coordinated plan for the District of Columbia, 1944-1947; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1921-1980; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1931; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1931-1945; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1945; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1944-1953; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1946; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1952; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1957; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Urban America Inc., 1966-1971; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1971; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence [handwritten], undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Charles W. Eliot letters, 1978-1980; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Delta Upsilon Technology chapter, 1941-1958; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Economic History of Washington; research and writing by John Nolen, Jr., 1973; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Explorer's Club - Ehlers clippings, 1978; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - History of Federal Triangle, 1980; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - George Washington Canal, 1966; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Harvard College, 1941-1945; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - John Christopher Nolen high school diploma, 1950 January 26; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Loose materials, 1941-1971; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Mass. Society, 1950-1952; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - MIT, 1980; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Obituaries and related letters, 1981-1984; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Photograph John Nolen, Sr. and Elizabeth Wheeler, undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Photograph [unidentified people], undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - H and T 45-50 reunion, 1964-1965; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Trip scrapbook, 1962-1964; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Scientific Urban Planning [1/2], 1972; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Scientific Urban Planning [2/2], 1972; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Scientific planning for urban living, undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Washington, DC articles, 1961; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Writing of John Nolen, Jr., 1932-1934; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Planning organizations, 1925-1986; Series 2; 10.5 Linear Feet
  Organized into two subseries: National Capital Park and Planning Commission and Planning organizations.
  This series contains correspondence, speeches, reports, articles, and conference data for organizations for which John Nolen worked or was a member of as a professional urban planner. These records date from 1925-1986. One subseries contains record of Nolen's work with the the National Capital Park and Planning Commission (later the National Capital Planning Commission). Nolen served as City Planner and Director of Planning from 1931-1951 and from 1951-1958 he served as Director. The second subseies contains records of a variety of professional organizations that Nolen participated with during his career.
  - National Capital Park and Planning Commission, 1925-1983; Series 2 Subseries 1; 2 Linear Feet
    Arranged chronologically.
    This subseries contains correspondence, reports, studies, and minutes related to the working of the National Capital Park and Planning Commission. The name of the organization changed in 1952 to the National Capital Planning Commission. These records date from 1928-1983.
    Please note that series 5 contains oversize materials that do fit the subject of the National Capital Park and Planning Commission.
    History
    The U.S. Congress established the National Capital Park Commission, the predecessor of today's National Capital Planning Commission, in 1924 to ensure the implementation of the McMillan Plan. Over the next several years, Congress expanded the Commission's original mandate, endowing it with responsibility for the "comprehensive, systematic, and continuous development of the park, parkway, and playground systems of the National Capital and its environs."
    The 1952 passage of the National Capital Planning Act gave the Commission the name it bears today and established it as the central planning agency for the federal government in the National Capital Region, with its current form and functions. Congress also reiterated its charge to NCPC to preserve the region's important natural and historic features.
    The 1973 District of Columbia Home Rule Act delegated the District's planning responsibility to the city's mayor. The Act maintains NCPC's role as the central planning agency for federal land and buildings in the National Capital Region, with an advisory role to the District for certain land use decisions.
    Thanks to its tradition of planning, Washington, DC is one of the world's finest urban achievements. NCPC promotes a long-range vision for the development of the District and the surrounding area that respects the L'Enfant and McMillan legacies while meeting the needs of future generations.
    From the website of the NCPC http://www.ncpc.gov/ncpc/Main%28T2%29/About_Us%28tr2%29/About_Us%28tr3%29/History.html
    - Data and reports, 1925-1932; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Data and reports, 1927-1938; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Data and reports, 1930-1933; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Planning Education, 1929-1940; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Personnel, 1933-1936; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - National Capital Park and Planning Commission documents, 1933-1939; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Work notes, 1934-1936; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Georgetown traffic, 1934-1936; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Planning: Washington, DC, 1935; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - National Capital Park and Planning Commission, 1936; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Petworth Playground, 1936; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - National Capital Park and Planning Commission, 1938; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - National Capital Park and Planning Commission correspondence, 1937-1941; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - National Capital Park and Planning Commission, 1938-1939; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Progress reports on major projects, 1938-1939; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - National Capital Park and Planning Commission, 1940-1943; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - National Capital Park and Planning Commission, 1940; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - National Capital Park and Planning Commission, Circa 1940; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Juvenile crime, 1940; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - National Capital Park and Planning Commission correspondence, 1940; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - National Capital Park and Planning Commission Nolen file Zoning, 1940-1941; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - National Capital Park and Planning Commission Nolen file, 1943; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - National Capital Park and Planning Commission Nolen file zoning, 1944; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - National Capital Park and Planning Commission, 1944; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - National Capital Park and Planning Commission documents [1/2], 1944; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - National Capital Park and Planning Commission documents [2/2], 1944; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - National Capital Park and Planning Commission community war service, 1944-1945; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - National Capital Park and Planning Commission correspondence, 1944-1957; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - National Capital Park and Planning Commission, 1947-1955; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - National Capital Park and Planning Commission, 1948-1952; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence Prof. and Office, 1948-1958; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1950-1953; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence from Frederick Bigger, 1951-1954; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - H.R. 7502 Reorganization Bill House Dist. Committee Hearings, 1952 June 3; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Assignment of playgrounds park system, 1953 January; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1953-1955; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - National Park and Planning Commission, 1953; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Zoning, 1954-1955; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - National Capital Park and Planning Commission, 1954-1955; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Position descriptions, 1954-1955; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence (chairman), 1954-1956; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Schedule and appointments, 1954-1956; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Mass transportation survey financial statements and appropriations, 1955-1957; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1955-1960; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Status of land acquisition and other funds monthly reports appropriations, 1957; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1953-1957; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence - professional (retain for reference), 1961-1972; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Urban Design and Development Corporation, 1969-1976; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - C-5 Pennsylvania Avenue Development District, 1978; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Comprehensive plan, 1968; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Comprehensive plan, 1983; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Comprehensive plan, 1983; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Planning organizations, 1928-1986; 1935-1965; Series 2 Subseries 2; 8.5 Linear Feet
    This subseries contains correspondence, brochures, reports, and minutes related to the workings of various professional organizations related to urban planning. Some of these organizations are ones that John Nolen worked with in a professional capacity and some are organizations of which he was an involved member. The organizations include The American Society of Civil Engineers, American Institute of Planners, Committee of 100 on the Federal City, the Torch Club of Washington, and the GW Chapter of Lambda Alpha. The records date from 1928-1986.
    - AAA Highway Committee, 1950-1952; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - American Institute of Architects urban planning group, Washington DC Chapter, 1943 April 7-21; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - American City Planning Institute, 1935-1936; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - American City Planning Institute, 1936-1937; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - American City Planning Institute, 1938-1939; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - American Institute of Planners programs and committee reports, 1941-1948; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - American Institute of Planners, 1944-1945; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - American Institute of Planners, 1945; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - American Institute of Planners, 1945; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - American Institute of Planners membership applications J.N.Jr. sponsor etc., 1945-1955; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - American Institute of Planners secretary-treasurer, 1946-1947; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - American Institute of Planners Finance Committee, 1947-1949; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - American Institute of Planners Correspondence on committee reports [1/2], 1948-1954; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - American Institute of Planners Correspondence on committee reports [2/2], 1948-1954; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - American Institute of Planners Board of Governors, 1948 January - 1949 March; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - American Institute of Planners Meeting programs and committee reports, 1949-1953; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - American Institute of Planners National affairs - general, 1953-1957; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - American Institute of Planners A.S.L.A [American Society of Landscape Architects] joint committee, 1952 December - 1955 November; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - American Institute of Planners banquet photograph, 1955 April 1; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - American Institute of Planners Kansas City Mtg., 1955 March 31 -April 2; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - American Institute of Planners Washington Chapter, 1946 November - 1955 June; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - American Institute of Planners National affairs - general, 1959; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - American Institute of Planners Transportation policy, 1964; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - American Institute of Planners, 1965-1967; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - American Planning and Civic Association, 1936; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - American Planning and Civic Association Committee of 100, 1949-1960; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - American Planning and Civic Association Annual meeting, Washington DC J.N.Jr speech and citation, 1956; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers Bicentennial Committee, 1973-1974; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers Bicentennial Committee drafts of agendas, minutes and resolutions, 1947-1975; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers Bicentennial Committee, 1974-1975; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers Bicentennial Committee NSF applications, 1975; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers Bicentennial Committee NSF applications, 1976; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers Bicentennial Committee NSF applications, 1975-1976; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers Bicentennial Committee NSF applications, 1976-1977; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers Bicentennial Committee, 1977-1978; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers Bicentennial Committee final report material, undated; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers Bicentennial Committee final report, undated; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers Bicentennial Committee work papers, undated; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers city planning division, 1941-1942; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers city planning division charmansky files, 1943-1944; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers city planning division publications committee, 1954-1957; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers City Planning Division Committee on Cooperation with local sections, undated; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers City Planning Division, undated; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers Conference, 1944; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers Fall convention Technical Program Committee, 1949; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers correspondence, 1944-1945; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers District of Columbia section, 1942-1959; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers District of Columbia section, 1937-1950; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers Environmental Engineering Tech. Committee, 1965; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers Environmental Engineering Committee, 1965-1966; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers Environmental Engineering Committee, 1969-1973; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers George Washington Canal and Locks Committee, 1954-1956; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - American Society of Civil Engineers George Washington Canal and Locks Committee, 1967-1969; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 17, Folder 3)